let's talk now about operations on processes
so one sort of intuitive thing here is that of course
the operating system
needs to provide mechanisms to create processes
now as you can imagine if you let's say double
click on your
screen something so that you can start a process
it means
that there is a process that is listening
to your double
click and as a result of this it creates a
new process
so in fact each process you execute has a parent
process
that is the one that is actually creating
the process
and if you look at all the processes that
are running at
the same time meaning
that they are
either ready or running depending on how many
cores you
have or waiting at the same time in your operating
system
you will see that they form a tree structure
each process has an unique id
that is the identifier
and when you create processes the operating
system gives
you the possibility to express a bit how you
want these processes
to share resources for example with respect
to their parent
process and also how you want to execute them
at the same
time with the parent or maybe they first execute
and the parent
waits for them to terminate and so on and so
forth
so this is how it looks in a Unix operating
system
so you have the init process is the very first
process and
it has process
id one
and then all the rest is a child of this process
and all the
processes are connected in a tree structure
so you have the process that manages clients
logging in into the
system and the parent of this process
is init
you have the one that can manage ssh connections
and so and
so forth
and you can actually check by yourself
you can just run this command check the manual
to understand
what it does and what are its options
and you will see that all the processes are
actually organized
in a tree if you look at their parent-child
or parent-children
relation so now let's look at a specific example
of how
you do this using the functionality of the
operating system
so we are going to look at two system calls
fork and exec
the idea is that we will start with one process
this process will call fork
and from that point on there will be two processes
the
parent one that is the one that is calling
fork that will
wait and the child one that will call another
system call
use exec do something and eventually exit
this will get more familiar also when you
lab 1 and
the shell
but before that fork is a system call that
creates a new
process the way it creates the process is
that it creates
an exact copy of the process that calls fork
so if you write a program and then you execute
it as a process
and at a certain point you call the system
call fork
if everything works well then you will create
a new process
that is an exact copy of the original one
the exec system call is usually used after
fork what it does
is that it replaces the memory of the process
with that of
another process
and then executes that process
let's have a look at this
so this is an example in c
i'm not going to go through all the instructions
is just
to show you what is happening
when we call these system comes
so we create a process and it starts running
and there is a series of instructions that
will be executed
in the text portion of the process
we create a variable called id
and then we set the value of this variable
to the
result of the function the system call
fork
this is what I just said
this is the system call that will create a
new process and
make it a copy of the existing one
so when we call this method we are basically
telling the
operating system please create a new process
that will eventually
end up in the ready state and then running
when there is
CPU time
and this process should be an exact copy of
myself where
I am the process that is invoking fork
if everything goes well now we have two
processes
and they are two exact same copies of each other
what does it mean that both will have a text
section that
has this code
the parent as well as the child will run as
the next instruction
the instruction that comes after the fork
okay so let's see what that means
both will run this instruction here
we are checking if the value returned by fork
is less than
zero if that is the case there is an error
so the child process was not created and
then we exit
in this case since fork did not work we only
have one process
so it's only the parent process that is the
one that is going
to execute these instructions
otherwise if the value of pid is zero then
it's going to
call this exec and it's going to replace his
memory with the
command ls which is the command use to list
the content of
a folder
if that is not the case so pid is greater
than zero then
the process will wait until the child process
is finished
this is the parent process and then it will
print child
complete so what is happening here?
if work works well there will be two processes
and they
are two copies 1 of the other
how do you differentiate between the parent and
the child?
if you do that because the operating system
gives you a
different result output into the value of
the variable pid
if you are the child process then this value
will be zero
this of course does not mean that the process
id of the
child is zero
this is the value of the variable process
id
if the value you get is greater than zero
then you are the
parent in that case the value you get is actually
the process id
of the child
now depending on the value you get you
can decide
whether you want to execute the code of the
child or the
code of the parent as you have functionality
to create processes
of course you also have functionality to terminate
processes
when you run your last instruction you can
exit the process
calling the exit function or the exit system
call
in this case you are telling to the operating
system that
you are done and you can give back a return
value to the
parent process that might be waiting for you
because we always have a parent process
remember everything is organized into a tree
if you look at the parent and children relationship
on the
other hand the parent might also terminate
the execution of the children with
another system
call which is the abort
this is one of the reasons why you get the
id of the child
process has a return of the fork because if
you want to
do operations over them and you in this case
are the parent
then you need the ids to specify to the operating
system
for instance which is the process you want
to abort
notice that whether a process can run or not
and how it can
run depends on how the operating system is
implemented
some operating system might not allow the
child process to
exist if the parent has terminated while others
might say
well the child can still execute even if the
parent has
terminated if the parent wants to wait for
the child or
the children to terminate then the operating
system gives
you this possibility
and this is the wait system call
that is what I show you before we have these
two terms zombie
and orphan
so if no parent is waiting because they did
not involve wait
then the process the child process is a zombie
if the parent terminated without invoking
wait then the
process is an orphan
this is the terms we use
now you might ask why would I create a process
that is an
exact copy of myself?
well there are different reasons we will discuss
them and
we will also see that the operating system
is pretty smart
despite the fact that it creates a copy
it has a mechanism to create such a copy that
is extremely
efficient but we will discuss this later on
but an example
that probably use frequently is the chrome
browser
so when you run chrome you are running a set
of processes
and you have one process for each tab
this is done because if a tab crashes or let's
say if there
is a problem with getting information for
a specific tab
you don't freeze the entire chrome
but you only experience this problem for a
specific tab
you can see an example since each process
that is a tab
is exactly the same
actually creating copies using the fork
mechanism should
make a lot of sense
hopefully